American Youth Congress Collection
American Youth Congress Collection
1937-1944
American Youth Congress.
2 linear ft.
Correspondence, minutes, publications, radio scripts, more from the youth organization active from 1935 to 1940.
2705303
Biographical History
The American Youth Congress was formed in 1935 to be a "voice for youth" on economic, social, and political issues of interest to young people, including unemployment, education, the draft, Communism, and so on. The organization was structured like a mock Congress, with delegates from across the United States as well as Canada, Cuba, China, Puerto Rico, and other countries. First Lady Eleanor Roosevelt was a strong backer of the organization (her involvement eventually led to the establishment of the National Youth Administration). When leaders of the AYC were subpoenaed by the House Un-American Affairs Committee (HUAC), Mrs. Roosevelt attended the hearings to demonstrate her support. The organization disbanded in 1940, largely due to internal conflict over the Nazi-Soviet non-aggression pact.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The American Youth Congress Collection consists of correspondence, publications, and subject files.
Correspondence is that of the AYC with external individuals and organizations. Represented here are a range of liberal, leftist, progressive, and youth-focused organizations such as the Carnegie Endowmen for International Peace and the United Student Peace Committee. There is also correspondence with individuals, some supporters and others who were interested in the AYC as a phenomenon.
Publications of the AYC include several issues of three different newsletters and a "Delegates Manual" in newspaper format.
Subject files relate to internal AYC committees (Education Commission, Far East Commissions, Jobs Commission) and projects (Youth In Focus, American Youth Act) as well as including general AYC papers, including minutes and financial records. This series also includes typescript of radio programs, dramatized scenarios and conversations dealing with various youth-oriented questions and problems.
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has numerous collections relating to American radicalism. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Carlson, Mildred.; Colby, Merle, 1902-1969.; American Youth Congress.; Socialism and youth -- United States.; Youth -- United States -- Congresses.; Youth -- United States -- Political activity.; Youth protest movements.; Correspondence.; Newsletters.; Clippings (information artifacts); Minutes (administrative records); Press releases.; Radio scripts.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Adah C. Blackman Fund, 2009.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Carlson, Mildred, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Cerf, Bennett, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Colby, Merle, 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Council of Social Agencies of Chicago, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Creel, Randall, 1940; regarding ROTC, Joseph Curran of the Seaman's Union (Box 1)
  - Immigration and Naturalization Service (INS), 1938-1940 (Box 1)
  - International Alliance of Women for Suffrage and Equal Citizenship, 1939 (Box 1)
  - International Youth Council in Britain, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Leslie, Kenneth, 1942; includes draft of article on pacificism among Christian youth, possibly by a Dr. Vlastos (Box 1)
  - Stone, Candace, 1939-1940; regarding National Youth Center and Year-Round Hostel, and a proposed book on youth activities (Box 1)
  - United Student Peace Committee, 1937; undated; includes letter from Federal Union of Spanish Students (Box 1)
  - IBM (International Business Machines), 1938; mentions IBM's loan of their Filene-Finlay Translator System for the 2d Congress (Box 1)
- Publications
  - "Delegates Manual" (newspaper format) (Oversize 1)
  - Newsletters
    - AYC News, 1940; 3 issues (Box 1)
    - Newscast, 1941; 7 issues (Box 1)
    - Youth, 1938; 1939; 4 issues (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, brochures, fliers, etc. (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - American Youth Act (Box 1)
  - Education Commission, 1937; memo on "The function of education in a democracy" (Box 1)
  - Far Eastern Commission, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Financial material, 1942-1944 (Box 1)
  - Jobs commission
    - Minutes, 1940 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Radio scripts, undated (Box 1)
    - Titled, titles include "Freedom Under Fire" and "Mr. Youth Goes to Washington" (Box 1)
    - Untitled (Box 1)
  - Youth in Focus project (Oversize 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)